James Monroe Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
James Monroe Papers 1758-1839
MSS33217
Monroe, James, 1758-1831
5,200 items
50 containers plus 1 oversize
16 linear feet
13 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
United States president, secretary of state, secretary of war, and diplomat; delegate to the Continental Congress from and governor of Virginia. Correspondence relating primarily to negotiations for the Louisiana Purchase, the Monroe-Pinkney treaty with Great Britain, the War of 1812, the purchase of Florida, South American independence, and Virginia politics and a diary, an account book of memoranda and official and personal accounts, and other papers.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Adams, John Quincy, 1767-1848--Correspondence.; Adams, John, 1735-1826--Correspondence.; Armstrong, John, 1758-1843--Correspondence.; Barlow, Joel, 1754-1812--Correspondence.; Benton, William, 1788-1881--Correspondence.; Bowdoin, James, 1752-1811--Correspondence.; Calhoun, John C. (John Caldwell), 1782-1850--Correspondence.; Crawford, William Harris, 1772-1834--Correspondence.; Dearborn, Henry, 1751-1829--Correspondence.; Erskine, Thomas Erskine, Baron, 1750-1823--Correspondence.; Erving, George William, 1769-1850--Correspondence.; Gallatin, Albert, 1761-1849--Correspondence.; Graham, John, 1774-1820--Correspondence.; Henderson, Richard H., active 1822--Correspondence.; Humphreys, David, 1752-1818--Correspondence.; Jackson, Andrew, 1767-1845--Correspondence.; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826--Correspondence.; Jones, Joseph, 1727-1805--Correspondence.; King, Rufus, 1755-1827--Correspondence.; Law, Thomas, 1756-1834--Correspondence.; Livingston, Robert R., 1746-1813--Correspondence.; Madison, James, 1751-1836--Correspondence.; McLean, John, 1785-1861--Correspondence.; Mercer, John Francis, 1759-1821--Correspondence.; Monroe, James, 1758-1831.; Pinkney, William, 1764-1822--Correspondence.; Randolph, Edmund, 1753-1813--Correspondence.; Randolph, John, 1773-1833--Correspondence.; Roane, Spencer, 1762-1822--Correspondence.; Rodney, C. A. (Caesar Augustus), 1772-1824--Correspondence.; Rush, Richard, 1780-1859--Correspondence.; Taylor, John, 1753-1824--Correspondence.; Tazewell, Littleton Waller, 1774-1860--Correspondence.; Tucker, St. George, 1752-1827--Correspondence.; Washington, George, 1732-1799--Correspondence.; Wirt, William, 1772-1834--Correspondence.
Subjects
Louisiana Purchase.
Places
Florida--History--Spanish colony, 1784-1821.; France--Foreign relations--United States.; Great Britain--Foreign relations--Treaties.; Great Britain--Foreign relations--United States.; South America--History--Wars of Independence, 1806-1830.; Spain--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Foreign relations--1783-1865.; United States--Foreign relations--France.; United States--Foreign relations--Great Britain.; United States--Foreign relations--Spain.; United States--Foreign relations--Treaties.; United States--History--1783-1865.; United States--History--War of 1812.; United States--Politics and government--1817-1825.; Virginia--Politics and government.
Titles
James Monroe Papers at the Library of Congress
Occupations
Cabinet officers.; Delegates, U.S. Continental Congress--Virginia.; Diplomats.; Presidents--United States.
Acquisition Information
The papers of James Monroe, United States president, secretary of state, secretary of war, and diplomat, delegate to the Continental Congress from and governor of Virginia, consist of material received through gift, transfer from the United States State Department, and purchase by the Library of Congress during the years 1901-2001.
Additional Guides
The microfilm edition of these papers (not including additions) is indexed in the Index to the James Monroe Papers (Washington, D.C.: 1963), prepared as part of the President's Papers Index Series. The index is available online at https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.gdc/gdclccn.62060006.
Other Repositories
Microfilm of James Monroe papers in the New York Public Library, New York, N.Y., and a microfilm produced by the University of Virginia Library of records in the Virginia State Archives and other Virginia repositories are available for consultation in the Manuscript Division reading room.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of James Monroe are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of part of these papers is available on thirteen reels. Consult reference staff in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition as available.
Online Content
The papers of James Monroe are available on the Library of Congress Web site at https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/collmss.ms000029. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the online edition as available.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1758, April 28 Born, Westmoreland County, Va.
1774 Moved to King George County under the guardianship of his uncle, Joseph Jones Entered College of William and Mary, Williamsburg, Va.
1775 Commissioned second lieutenant, Third Virginia Regiment
1775 1779 Fought with George Washington and William Alexander in New York, New Jersey, and Pennsylvania, rising to the rank of lieutenant colonel
1779 Studied law with Thomas Jefferson in Williamsburg, Va.
1782 Representative, King George County, Virginia House of Delegates
1783 1786 Delegate from Virginia, Fourth Congress of the Confederation
1786 Married Elizabeth Kortright (died 1830) Practiced law, Fredericksburg, Va.
1788 Delegate to the Virginia state convention to ratify the Federal constitution
1790 1794 Senator from Virginia, First Congress of the United States
1794 1796 Minister Plenipotentiary to France
1799 1803 Governor of Virginia
1803 Minister Plenipotentiary to France; signed Louisiana Purchase
1803 1807 Minister to England
1811 Governor of Virginia
1811 1817 Secretary of state
1813 Secretary of war, ad interim
1814 Joined Maryland militia at Bladensburg
1814 1815 Secretary of war and secretary of state, acting in dual appointments
1817 1825 President of the United States
1830 Moved to New York, N.Y., to make his home with daughter Maria and son-in-law Samuel Gouverneur
1831, July 4 Died, New York, N.Y.
History of the Collection
[From Index to the James Monroe Papers (Washington, D.C.: 1963), pp. v-xi]
When James Monroe retired from the Presidency on March 4, 1825, he returned to Oak Hill, his estate in Loudoun County, Va. [1] In the years that followed, his attempts to pay his debts and to better his financial condition must have required the steady use of a great many of the papers he had accumulated during his long years of public service, particularly those which could further the investigation of his accounts that he had asked Congress to make. Annotations on many of the papers give evidence that Monroe made some attempt to organize them; this was doubtless done during the years of his retirement.
To stimulate action by Congress he wrote a long paper on his "unsettled claims" in the summer of 1826 and sent it to Gales and Seaton in Washington for publication. [2] The following year he undertook the preparation of two additional papers which he hoped would raise money through sales. The first of these was a comparison of the Government of the United States with other, older, republics; [3] the second was his autobiography. [4]
Another means of raising money was suggested to him in correspondence with Nicholas P. Trist, who wrote him on January 27, 1828, from Monticello:
I suppose you have kept copies of all yr. letters to Mr. J[efferson].—There are among them numerous evid[en]ces of the pure disinterestedness of yr. course, & of the fact that in taking those steps wh. launched you irrevocably on the sea of public life, you were actuated solely by devotion to yr. country, to the well understood disparagemt. of yr. individual interests. That you may reap a reward somewhat commensurate with these sacrifices is with me more a wish than a hope. Will you permit me to ask however whether you cd. not at once avail yourself of the value of yr. papers, by pledging the proceeds of their future public[atio]n, in consid[eratio]n of a loan? If I mistake not, such a measure would be far from unexampled; wd. it be impracticable?
In Monroe's reply, on February 8, he wrote: "I have examined my papers, and find that I have, as I believe, all the letters, that were ever written to me by Mr. Jefferson. The first bears date in 1780, while I was reading the law under him.... I have copies, but I am satisfied, that I have not, of a fifth, of them I wrote him." He offered to send Jefferson's letters to Thomas Jefferson Randolph if he would be gratified to possess them, an offer that was apparently not accepted, and he added: "Your suggestion as to the sale of my papers, or pledge of them, merits attention." [5]
Monroe's study of republics and his autobiography were incomplete, and his claims before Congress were still unresolved, when Mrs. Monroe died in September 1830. Two months later financial difficulties and ill health forced him to leave Oak Hill and to make his home with his younger daughter, Maria, and her husband, Samuel L. Gouverneur, in New York City. The latter was acting as Monroe's agent in dealing with the several committees of Congress investigating his claims, and for this purpose Monroe had supplied his son-in-law with selections from his papers from time to time, as shown in letters exchanged by the two men. In addition to papers that might already have been in New York, it is reasonable to suppose that Monroe took with him when he left Virginia such papers as he would need to continue work on his autobiography. Nevertheless, an undetermined number of his papers were at Oak Hill when Monroe died in New York City on July 4, 1831. [6]
In his will, Samuel L. Gouverneur was named "sole and exclusive executor" and was asked to care for Monroe's older daughter Elizabeth, whose husband, Judge George Hay, had died the previous autumn. The Monroe papers were mentioned somewhat obliquely in the following provision: "... with respect to the works in which I am engaged and leave behind, I commit the care and publication of them to my son in law Samuel L. Gouvernieur [sic], giving to him one third of the profits arising therefrom for his trouble in preparing them for publication, one third to my daughter Maria and one third to my daughter Elizabeth." [7]
In the first month of Gouverneur's proprietorship of the papers, he lent a small number to John Quincy Adams, who was to deliver a eulogy to Monroe in Boston at the invitation of the city government. On July 19, Gouverneur wrote: "As a means of affording you all the interesting details of Mr. Monroe's early life, in the most ample form, and with the greatest precision, I have taken the liberty to enclose you the first 60 or 70 sheets of a sketch prepared by himself, & which together with all his other interesting papers, he entrusted to my special charge.... With the history of his life for the later years, you are well acquainted. He has left copious notes & a most extensive correspondence but he was prevented by death, from completing that portion of his career, even in the shape, which the present has assumed." Apparently he sent additional papers a week later, because Adams, in a letter of August 30, wrote that he was returning "the papers transmitted to me with your letter of the 26th. ulto." and added that "The manuscript of Mr. Monroe shall be returned in the course of a few days—By a private hand if an opportunity should present itself. Before the end of the week I hope to forward a printed Copy of the Eulogy."
Early the following year Richard Rush, writing from York, Pa., asked Gouverneur to return the personal letters he had written to Monroe while he was minister to England: "I wrote often to him, and with a freedom that would not have been justifiable in my public despatches.... It is on this account that I should be glad to have them in my possession, lest by any chances hereafter any portion of them should come to be mixed up with his manuscripts... and in that way run the risk of publicity." The nature of Gouverneur's reply is suggested by the next letter he received from Rush: "Its obliging sentiments... leave me no anxiety on the score of the private and confidential letters alluded to.... if any parts of them can, in the judgement of others, be made subsidiary to the better understanding of any of Mr. Monroe's services, there is no scruple even that I would not forego on my part; so much did I honor him as a statesman, revere him as a patriot, and love him as a man. At the same time the promise you are so good as to give that no use will be made of any paper from me without my approbation... is a relief."
Gouverneur was again reminded of his responsibilities as custodian of the Monroe papers three years later, when he received an anonymous letter written by "A Virginian" in "Alexandria, District of Columbia," on June 11, 1835: "... the character of your illustrious kinsman is already marked a victim for the sacrifice.
Let me implore you as you revere his name and reverence his memory—let me intreat you as patriot and an honorable man—let me caution you as you value your own reputation hold on to every scrap of writing that may be in your possession in any manner connected with his private or public life—preserve every paper that concerns him, for as you life [sic], if you respect his memory you will have use for them.
Apparently Gouverneur did some work toward preparing the papers for publication during the 1830's and a manuscript relating to Monroe, which he started to write, is said to have survived. [8] He was busy with other pursuits, however—he was Postmaster of New York City from 1828 to 1836 and part owner of the Bowery Theatre there—and he seems not to have found work on the Monroe papers a congenial occupation. Nevertheless there is no evidence that he was ready to accept the offer of help he received from Barnabus Bates of New York City, who, in a letter of February 13, 1839, agreed to prepare and publish a memoir on Monroe "upon terms which shall be mutually advantageous and satisfactory." Bates had heard through Commodore Charles Goodwin Ridgely, then in charge of the Navy Yard at New York, that Gouverneur possessed "a very interesting correspondence between Presdts. Jefferson and Monroe in relation to the Gun Boat system recommended by the former," and he suggested that Gouverneur "procure while in Virginia any papers necessary to accomplish the object."
In contrast Gouverneur took positive action in regard to the papers during the following decade.
Elizabeth Kortright Hay, Monroe's older daughter, died in 1840 and in the same year Samuel and Maria Gouverneur moved from New York City to Washington, where they lived in the De Menou buildings on H Street. [9] They also spent periods of each year at Oak Hill. Gouverneur worked in the Consular Bureau of the Department of State from 1844 to 1849, when he resigned because of the "afflicted state" of his family and because a promised advancement had not materialized. [10]
It must have been about the time he entered Government service that Gouverneur became acquainted with Henry O'Reilly (or O'Rielly, as he later spelled his name), a vigorous young man who had been editor of the Rochester Daily Advertiser in Rochester, N.Y., and who was active in many causes. According to a long, rather rambling memorandum O'Reilly wrote many years later, Gouverneur first tried to persuade him to occupy the farm at Oak Hill and to assist in disposing of the property, and later Gouverneur sought his help in connection with the Monroe papers: "In the course of our acquaintance Mr. Gouverneur suggested to me, without any solicitation on my part, that he & others wished me to take charge & control of the Ex-President's records & other Papers with a view to the Publication of A Selection from those papers along with a memoir of Mr. Monroe &c in case it should be found that a sale of the whole mass could not be made to the Government.... [11]
Gouverneur did indeed turn over to O'Reilly what appears to have been in the major part of the Monroe papers, probably in 1844 or 1845. In the latter year O'Reilly also entered into a contract with Samuel F. B. Morse and Amos Kendall to raise capital for telegraph lines from Eastern Pennsylvania to St. Louis and the Great Lakes, and his work in this connection must have left him little time to give to the Monroe papers. Even their exact location during the mid-1840's is uncertain although glancing references in some of his letters make it likely that O'Reilly deposited them somewhere in New York City while his work of erecting telegraph lines took him from place to place. Samuel L. Gouverneur himself seems not to have known where they were being stored. His concern is evident in a letter he wrote to O'Reilly on May 17, 1847, in which he also outlined terms for the treatment of the papers: "I should have written you before—but from the uncertainty where a letter would find you—I see by the papers (notices of arrivals, etc.) that you are in New York [actually this letter was forwarded to Philadelphia].
I propose in reply to yours that we should divide the proceeds—first deducting 1/8 to be allowed to the Estate of Mr. Monroe. This is on the supposition that the Heirs at law might expect something, & I should agree to fix the sum at that. I also wish it stipulated that the entire control of published matter in reference to Mr. Monroe should be vested in me—I mean that no papers should be published without my assent first had. This I consider just & right, especially as some matter might refer to questions of a personal or delicate nature. Let me have your reply to the above.
I hope you have the papers all in a place of perfect security as I value them very highly, & would be unwilling to run the risk of loss or accident to them—when will you be this way—I should be glad to have a talk with you... ."
Not having heard from O'Reilly, Gouverneur wrote again nearly five months later, on October 14, asking him to drop a line and "assure me respecting which, I feel some anxiety, that all my papers, are safely deposited, where no accident can befall them." This letter apparently reached O'Reilly in Cincinnati, Ohio. [12]
The first and apparently only substantial use that was made of the Monroe Papers while they were in Gouverneur's custody occurred the following year. Gouverneur requested O'Reilly to make transcripts of a number of papers for Senator James D. Westcott, Jr., of Florida, and he himself lent the Senator a parcel of original manuscripts he had retained. The texts or references to these were incorporated in Westcott's speech of July 25, 1848, on the territorial government of Oregon. [13]
The stalemate on making effective arrangements to publish or sell the Monroe papers seems finally to have been broken in 1848. Doubtless an important factor in this matter was the purchase made by the Government that year of papers of James Madison (a second segment), of Alexander Hamilton, and of Thomas Jefferson. On December 14, Richard Smith, the executor of Elizabeth K. Hay's estate, agreed to accept one-eighth of the proceeds of any publication or sale (rather than the one-third share specified in James Monroe's will) provided the estate was exonerated from any costs connected with the transactions. [14] This was followed on December 28 by a formal agreement between Samuel L. Gouverneur and Henry O'Reilly, by which any profits resulting from publication of the papers would be divided so as to give three-eighths to O'Reilly, one-eighth to the estate of President Monroe, and four-eighths to Gouverneur. If, however, the papers were sold for not less than $20,000, O'Reilly was to get thirty percent of the proceeds and to pay one-third of this amount to Eliab Kingman and others assisting in the sale, while Gouverneur was to get the other seventy percent and to pay from this sum one-eighth of the entire proceeds to the estate of James Monroe. [15]
Upon completion of these arrangements Gouverneur addressed a petition to Congress on January 1, 1849, asking aid from the Government in publishing the manuscript papers of James Monroe. [16] Presented by Senator John A. Dix of New York on January 3, the petition was ordered to be printed and referred to the Committee on the Library. [17] Gouverneur apparently learned later that month that the Congress preferred to purchase the manuscripts rather than subscribe to their publication, and at this point O'Reilly, through an agent, formally relinquished his rights under the contract with Gouverneur so that the purchase could proceed without complication. [18] On February 28 the Senate, by a vote of 28 to 20, approved the purchase of the Monroe papers for $20,000. On March 2 the House concurred in an amendment proposed by the Committee of Ways and Means that the purchase be limited to papers not of a private character; [19] and on the following day it was enacted, as part of the act making appropriations for the civil and diplomatic expenses of Government for the year ending June 30, 1850, that "the manuscript books and papers of the late James Monroe" be purchased for the above amount and be deposited in the Department of State. [20] On March 13 Gouverneur signed an indenture of bargain and sale of "all the said Manuscript Books & Papers of the said James Monroe, together with all copyright, title, interest, property, claim & demand whatsoever of, in, and to the same," and on the same day the transaction was completed when Secretary of State John M. Clayton signed a receipt for the material and First Auditor William Collins signed a certificate that the sum of $20,000 was payable to Samuel L. Gouverneur as executor of the estate of James Monroe." [21]
Historian James Schouler was perhaps the first person to use the Monroe papers for historical research while they were in the Department of State. In 1882 he described them as "a huge mass of interesting matter relative to our earlier national history, which lies unassorted in the Department of State and for whose editorial supervision and publication it is to be fervently hoped that Congress will some day make suitable provision." [22]
This situation was rectified when Congress, by acts approved March 2, 1889, and August 30, 1890, appropriated money for the repair, mounting, and binding of the papers. [23] They were arranged in two chronological series (one comprising manuscripts by Monroe, the other manuscripts addressed or referred to him) and were bound in 22 volumes. A calendar of the papers, which reflected the two series but with entries arranged alphabetically by writer of each manuscript, was prepared and published by the Department of State in preliminary form in 1889 and in a corrected edition in 1893. [24] Seven years later the Librarian of the Department of State prepared a seven-volume unofficial edition of the writings of Monroe. [25]